{"tossups": [{"question": "In her twenties, this chemistry teacher worked at Chicago\u2019s Hull House, before attending the Wharton School. As head of the National Consumers' League, this woman witnessed the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire, leading to her appointment to the Committee of Safety. With a first lady, this woman organized the She-She-She camps in her highest office. For ten points, name this first female cabinet member, the Secretary of Labor under Franklin D. Roosevelt.", "answer": "Frances <b><u>Perkins</u></b> (or Fannie Coralie <b><u>Perkins</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This proposal came out of a series of meetings with several Barnburners like Preston King and Hannibal Hamlin. Voting on this proposal immediately followed a proposal by Indiana Democrat William A. Wick to simply extend the line of the Missouri Compromise. Attached as a rider to a two million dollar appropriations bill to end the Mexican-American War, for ten points, what was this unsuccessful 1846 proposal by a Pennsylvania Democrat to ban slavery in the newly won territories?", "answer": "<b><u>Wilmot</u></b> Proviso", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Michael VIII [[the eighth]] signed the Treaty of Nymphaeum [[nim-FAY-um]] with this polity, allowing trade concessions within the Byzantine Empire in exchange for fifty ships to push his claim to the throne. A Mongol siege of this state's port of Kaffa is hypothesized to be the origin of the Black Death in Europe. The 1768 Treaty of Versailles forced this Ligurian republic to cede Corsica to the Kingdom of France. For ten points, name this Northwestern Italian republic which fought many wars with the rival trade empire of Venice.", "answer": "The Most Serene Republic of <b><u>Genoa</u></b> (accept Seren\u00ecscima Rep\u00f9brica de <b><u>Z\u00eana</u></b>; or Repubblica di <b><u>Genova</u></b>; or Res Publica <b><u>Ianuensis</u></b>; also accept the Common Companions of <b><u>Genoa</u></b>; or Compagna Communis <b><u>Ianuensis</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Kit Carson scouts were former members of this organization who defected to the United States. Backed by the People's Army, this force killed 3,000 pro-American citizens in Hue [[WAY]] during the Tet Offensive. A northern country supplied armaments to this organization via the Ho Chi Minh Trail. A prolonged guerilla war against U.S. forces was fought by, for ten points, what communist paramilitary group during a mid-20th century war?", "answer": "<b><u>Viet Cong</u></b> (accept <b><u>National Liberation Front</u></b> of South Vietnam; or <b><u>M\u1eb7t tr\u1eadn D\u00e2n</u></b> <b><u>t\u1ed9c Gi\u1ea3i ph\u00f3ng</u></b> Mi\u1ec1n Nam Vi\u1ec7t Nam)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This general allied with Benito Juarez to battle the forces of Emperor Maximilian, eventually deposing and succeeding Sebastian Lerdo in his highest office. Factional strife between General Bernardo Reyes and the <em>cientificos</em> boiled over when this man declared himself winner of the presidency for the eighth time, after which he was the target of an uprising by Francisco Madero. For ten points, name this Mexican president immediately prior to the Mexican Revolution.", "answer": "Porfirio <b><u>D\u00edaz</u></b> (or Jos\u00e9 de la Cruz Porfirio <b><u>D\u00edaz</u></b> Mori)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Pausanias [[pow-SAN-ee-uss]] reported that the <em>polis</em> of Thebes claimed to have the bones of this hero. Roland's legendary sword Durendal was first forged for this man. Neoptolemus [[nee-op-TAH-leh-muss]] supposedly killed this man's infant son, Astyanax, by throwing him from the walls of a citadel. This man slew Patroclus while wearing the armor of his shield-brother. Achilles dragged the corpse of, for ten points, which Trojan hero and son of Priam?", "answer": "<b><u>Hector</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This man ironically published his memoir, <em>Permanent Record</em>, on September 17th which is also Constitution Day. This man is currently the head of the Board of Directors for the Freedom of the Press Foundation, having served in that role since 2016. In 2020, this man was finally granted asylum by the Russian government after fleeing the United States in 2013. For ten points, name this former NSA worker who leaked classified information about mass surveillance.", "answer": "Edward <b><u>Snowden</u></b> (or Edward Joseph <b><u>Snowden</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Near this city, ancient Greeks founded a settlement named Hesperis [[heh-SPEH-riss]] in the sixth century BC. This city thrived as a center of the Roman province of Cyrenaica [[sy-ruh-NAY-kah]]. After Italy granted independence to its North African colony, Tripoli and this city served as the Kingdom of Libya\u2019s two capitals. For ten points, name this Libyan city where Islamist militants attacked a U.S. diplomatic compound and killed four Americans, including Ambassador Chris Stevens.", "answer": "<b><u>Benghazi</u></b> [[ben-GAH-zee]]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Isaac Newton theorized this substance was composed of corpuscles in his book <em>Opticks</em>. That particle theory of polarization of this substance was mainstream until Robert Hooke developed the \"pulse theory\" and compared this form of radiation to waves of water in his book <em>Micrographia</em>. Years later, Max Planck [[PLAHNK]] described this type of radiation as a wave that can gain or lose finite amounts of energy, known as \"quanta.\" For ten points, name this type of electromagnetic radiation that can be seen by human eyes.", "answer": "Visible <b><u>Light</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "The name of this location in the Canaima [[kah-NAY-muh]] National Park is derived from the American aviator who first surveyed it from an airplane. In 2009, Venezuelan president Hugo Ch\u00e1vez argued for reinstating this geographical feature\u2019s indigenous name, <em>Kerepakupai Mer\u00fa</em> [[keh-reh-pah-KOO-pye meh-ROO]], which means \u201cwaterfall of the deepest place.\u201d For ten points, name this world\u2019s tallest uninterrupted waterfall which measures 3,212 feet.", "answer": "<b><u>Angel</u></b> Falls(or <b><u>Salto \u00c1ngel</u></b> [[AHN-hel]], or <b><u>Kerepakupai Mer\u00fa</u></b> [[keh-reh-PAH-koo-pye MEH-roo]] before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "An 1890 filibuster which planned to seize this region intended to appoint editor Warren Hastings as Governor-General. This region's \"South\" province rebelled against U.S. occupation during the Mexican-American War until the defeat of the rebels at San Jos\u00e9 del Cabo [[KAH-boh]]. It's not Nicaragua, but this region was captured by William Walker and incorporated into the Republic of Sonora. For ten points, identify this region now split into two Mexican states, where Walker occupied such cities as La Paz and Cabo San Lucas.", "answer": "<b><u>Baja</u></b> [[BAH-hah]] <b><u>California</u></b> (accept <b><u>Baja California</u></b> Sur; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man's unacknowledged abolitionist son, John Pierre, was born from a tryst with his Indian servant Mary Emmons. From 1808 to 1812, this man went on a self-imposed exile to England, where he befriended Utilitarian philosopher Jeremy Bentham. This New York lawyer received the second-highest amount of votes in one election, resulting in this man becoming vice president. For ten points, name this early leader of the Democratic-Republicans, the vice president under Thomas Jefferson.", "answer": "Aaron <b><u>Burr</u></b> Jr", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Shortly after the death of this nation's \"King-Imam\" Ahmad bin Yahya, Egyptian-trained officers deposed the House of Rassid [[RAH-seed]]. This nation's port of Mocha [[MOH-kuh]] was a major stopping point in the international coffee trade. The Zaydi movement originated in this country's Saada Governate, which was the epicenter of a 2010s civil war that followed the rise of the Houthis. The Aden Emergency hastened the end of British rule in, for ten points, what Middle Eastern nation governed from Sana'a?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Yemen</u></b> (or al-Jumh\u016br\u012byah al-<b><u>Yaman</u></b>\u012byah)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Rulers of this culture were known as <em>wanax</em>, and this culture is associated with a state known as Ahhiyawa [[ah-hee-YAH-wah]] in Hittite sources. The Lion\u2019s Gate was excavated at the entrance to the namesake city of this culture. It\u2018s not Troy, but that city of this culture was excavated by Heinrich Schliemann [[SHLEE-mahn]], who publicized a golden death mask he found there. Michael Ventris deciphered the Linear B script used by, for ten points, what Ancient Greek culture of the Late Bronze Age?", "answer": "<b><u>Mycenaean</u></b>s [[my-seh-NAY-ans]] (or <b><u>Mycenae</u></b>; prompt on \"Greek\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Most of Beach Boys member Dennis Wilson's possessions were stolen by acolytes of this man. This man predicted the occurrence of a race war between Blacks and whites which he named after a Beatles song. A former lover and follower of this man, \"Squeaky\" Fromme, attempted to assassinate President Gerald Ford in 1975. For ten points, name this cult leader, the head of a namesake \"Family\" who murdered actress Sharon Tate.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>Manson</u></b> (or Charles Milles <b><u>Manson</u></b>; or Charles Milles <b><u>Maddox</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The peace treaty ending this war led to a fifteen month \"Interim Peace\" and ceded one side's second-largest city of Viipuri [[VEE-poo-ree]]. This war saw the invention of Molotov [[MOH-loh-tohff]] cocktails. During this war, one side employed ski soldiers and a man called \"White Death,\" Simo H\u00e4yh\u00e4 [[SEE-moh HY-ah]]. Despite taking Karelia [[kah-REH-lyah]], the Soviets failed to reach Helsinki in, for ten points, what World War Two-era conflict which saw Finland maintain its independence?", "answer": "<b><u>Winter</u></b> War (or <b><u>First Finnish-Soviet</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In 2013, rapper Killah P was murdered in this country by a member of the Golden Dawn, which lost its last Parliamentary seat in 2019. This country's New Democracy party was founded in 1974 after the fall of the Regime of the Colonels. Syriza [[sih-REE-zah]] party leader Alexis Tsipras [[TSIP-rahss]] led this country through a period of austerity bookended by its third E.U. bailout. For ten points, name this country whose Prime Minister Kyriakos Mitsotakis [[kee-ree-AH-kohss mit-so-TAH-kiss]] came to power in 2019.", "answer": "<b><u>Greece</u></b> (or <b><u>Hellenic</u></b> Republic; or <b><u>Elliniki</u></b> Dimokratia; or <b><u>Hellas</u></b>; or <b><u>Ellas</u></b>; or <b><u>Ellada</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "One account tells how this figure became divine shortly before visiting the Alban colonist Proculus [[PRAH-kyoo-luss]], who states that he turned into a whirlwind and went to the heavens. This man organized games to commit the abduction of the Sabine [[SAY-been]] women. This descendant of Aeneas [[ay-NEE-ahss]] may have killed his sibling after arguing on which of seven hills to found this figure's namesake city. The legendary first king of Rome was, for ten points, which twin brother of Remus?", "answer": "<b><u>Romulus</u></b> [[ROM-yoo-luss]]", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In this colony, former indentured servant Maryn Adriansen committed a</u></b> <b><u>massacre of natives during Kieft's War. The Treaty of Breda formally handed over</u></b> <b><u>this colony to Charles II's England, and it was led by Director-General Peter (+)</u></b> <b>Stuyvesant [[STY-veh-sahnt]]. Using a cache of trade goods, including glass beads, Peter Minuit bought the island of (*) </b>Manhattan for this North American colonial venture. New Amsterdam served as the capital of, for ten points, what Dutch colonial venture in the Mid-Atlantic region of the modern U.S.?", "answer": "<b><u>New Netherland</u></b> (or <b><u>Nieuw Nederland</u></b>; prompt on \"New York\" or \"New Jersey\"; do not accept \"New Netherlands\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>While happening upon this event, Beat poet Allen Ginsberg allegedly said \u201cit\u2019s</u></b> <b><u>about time that we did something to assert ourselves.\u201d Sylvia Riviera has been</u></b> <b><u>mythologized as the person that \u201cthrew the first brick at [this event].\u201d This event,</u></b> <b><u>which occurred a week after Judy (+)</u> Garland\u2019s death, broke out after lesbian Storm\u00e9 DeLarverie [[stor-MAY deh-LAR-veh-ree]] was arrested and assaulted by (*) </b>New York police. For ten points, name this 1969 LGBTQ \u201criot\u201d that began at a Greenwich Village gay bar.", "answer": "<b><u>Stonewall</u></b> Inn Riot", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This war likely led to the victory of Lord Salisbury's Conservatives in the</u></b> <b><u>\"Khaki Election.\" A modified Maxim gun known as the \"Pom-Pom\" was introduced</u></b> <b><u>during this war, and its last two years degenerated into guerilla warfare under</u></b> <b><u>generals like Jan [[YAHN]] (+)</u> Smuts. The sieges of Kimberly and Mafeking [[MAH-feh-king]] occurred during this war, which was named for (*) </b>Dutch settlers of Africa. The Transvaal and the Orange Free State were incorporated into South Africa following, for ten points, what turn of the twentieth century conflict?", "answer": "Second <b><u>Boer</u></b> War (accept Second Anglo-<b><u>Boer</u></b> War; accept Second <b><u>South African</u> </b>War before \"South Africa\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Isser Harel called for a two year manhunt in this nation which aimed to bring</u></b> <b><u>Nazi war criminal Josef Mengele to justice. The dictator Jos\u00e9 Gaspar Rodr\u00edguez de</u></b> <b><u>Francia was known in this country as \"El Supremo.\" The Battle of Cerro Cor\u00e1 [[SEH-</u><u>roh koh-RAH]] saw the death of this country's president Francisco Solano (+)</u> L\u00f3pez, ending the six-year-long War of the Triple Alliance that pitted this country against three neighbors: Brazil, Argentina, and Uruguay. (*) </b>For ten points, name this landlocked South American country.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Paraguay</u></b> (or Republica del <b><u>Paraguay</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Due to failing to predict these events, the semi-mythical astrologers Hsi</u></b> <b><u>[[SEE]] and Ho were executed by a Xia [[SHYAH]] emperor. According to Herodotus,</u></b> <b><u>one of these events stopped a war between the Lydians and Medes since it was</u></b> <b><u>interpreted as a (+)</u> divine signal. An 1135 one of these phenomena coincided with the death of Henry I of England, associating these celestial events as an ill omen for rulers. The birth of (*) </b>Muhammad coincided with, for ten points, what type of celestial event in which the moon blocks all or part of the sun?", "answer": "Solar <b><u>Eclipse</u></b> (do not accept \"Lunar Eclipse\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Days prior to an event at this site, Mikhail Gorbachev met with a world leader</u></b> <b><u>for a summit at a nearby locale at the Great Hall of the People. A gathering in this</u></b> <b><u>location was precipitated by the death of the reformist Hu (+)</u> Yaobang [[HOO-YAO-BAHNG]]. Constructed during the Ming Dynasty in 1415, perhaps the most iconic photo taken at this location was of an unidentified man (*) </b>blocking tanks on a road. For ten points, name this Chinese location that was the site of mass protests and a massacre in 1989.", "answer": "<b><u>Tiananmen Square</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tiananmen Square</u></b> protests; accept <b><u>Tiananmen</u></b> <b><u>Square</u></b> massacre; prompt on \"Beijing\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Andres Segovia commissioned a composer from this nation, Heitor Villa-Lobos</u></b> <b><u>[[VEE-yah LOH-bohs]], to write a series of \u00e9tudes for classical guitar. This nation's</u></b> <b><u>commuter rail network is credited with spreading one musical genre out from the</u></b> <b><u>Est\u00e1cio neighborhood. (+)</u> Astrud Gilberto sang on \"Girl from Ipanema,\" which launched this nation's genre of Bossa Nova to worldwide popularity. Choro and (*) </b>Samba both originated in, for ten points, what country's city of Rio de Janeiro?", "answer": "Federative Republic of <b><u>Brazil</u></b> (or Rep\u00fablica Federativa do <b><u>Brasil</u></b>; accept Kingdom of <b><u>Brazil</u></b>; or Reino do <b><u>Brasil</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {"question": "<b><u>Li Mi of the Sui [[SWEH]] Dynasty constructed 300 of the \"Whirlwind\" variety</u></b> <b><u>of these machines to be placed on ships. During the Hrushevskoho [[hroo-shehv-</u><u>SKOH-hoh]] Street riots, a Kievan mob built one of these machines to hurl Molotov (*)</u></b> <b>cocktails at government buildings. The </b><em><b>Mangonel</b></em><b> was an early form of this siege engine brought from China, arriving in Medieval (*) </b>Europe by the 9th century. For ten points, what siege engine used a counterweight to fling objects?", "answer": "<b><u>Trebuchet</u></b> (or <b><u>Trebucket</u></b>; accept specific examples, such as the Traction <b><u>Trebuchet</u></b> or Counterpoise <b><u>Trebucet</u></b>; accept <b><u>Mangonel</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \"Catapult\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Scooter Libby was indicted after a member of this organization was publicly</u></b> <b><u>outed in the Plame Affair. This organization planned Operation Success from a</u></b> <b><u>Guatemala hotel room, plotting to overthrow President Jacobo [[hah-KOH-boh]] (+)</u></b> <b>Arbenz with Carlos Armas. The defection of Aldrich Ames to the USSR led to this organization losing all its active (*) </b>agents in Eastern Europe. The National Security Act of 1947 created, for ten points, which foreign intelligence apparatus of the U.S. government?", "answer": "<b><u>CIA</u></b> (or <b><u>Central Intelligence Agency</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}